<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Rob Lytle</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0ee476e0f8e52f1f1634ede288429d6f_11738_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vilifying the Victims of an Ineffectual State</title>
      <link>/post/banality-of-desantis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/banality-of-desantis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;














&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-ron-desantis-speaking-in-2017--photo-by-gage-skidmore&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://live.staticflickr.com/728/33090874326_d53c61e3fc_b.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Ron DeSantis speaking in 2017 | photo by Gage Skidmore&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://live.staticflickr.com/728/33090874326_d53c61e3fc_b.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Ron DeSantis speaking in 2017 | photo by Gage Skidmore
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

In a painfully predictable turn of events, COVID-19 cases have begun to skyrocket in Florida, a few short weeks after state and local government began the process of (prematurely) rolling back public health safeguards. This week, Governor Ron DeSantis performed an impressive rhetorical trick, abdicating not just his own responsibility for the death and illness—but that of all the wealthy consumers and business owners agitating for a return to normalcy at the expense of workers&amp;rsquo; lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desantis says 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/jun/20/florida-covid19-surge-reopening-governor-desantis-coronavirus&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re not shutting down. We&amp;rsquo;re going to go forward. We&amp;rsquo;re not rolling back. You have to have society function&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and that 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.miamiherald.com/news/coronavirus/article243685702.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The disease burden is not as significant as it was in March and April,&amp;rdquo; it&amp;rsquo;s “Very important to point out. We’re in a much better position than we were in March or April.”&lt;/a&gt;. According to DeSantis, to &amp;ldquo;shut down&amp;rdquo; (institute necessary and reasonable public health protections) the state now would do more harm to the people of Florida than the Coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, I take DeSantis at his word. I think he is entirely correct that &lt;em&gt;under his administration&lt;/em&gt; reinstating necessary physical distance and stay-at-home orders would be terrible for the median Floridian, but this is entirely by design. In the absence of a robust state or federal response, the second round of layoffs and furloughs would be financially ruinous for hundreds of thousands—if not millions—of Floridians, but this is a false dichotomy. DeSantis would have you believe that the paths forward are predetermined: either we can plunge the state and country into depression, or we can grease the gears of the economy with the infected sputum of the poorest and most vulnerable members of our society. DeSantis, like so many leaders, loathes using the power of the state to protect its people and is too craven to tell them as much. While countries like 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.canada.ca/en/revenue-agency/campaigns/covid-19-update/covid-19-benefits-credits-support-payments.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Canada&lt;/a&gt; deploy their modest social safety nets to ameliorate the economic costs of prudent health policy, executives and legislators in the U.S. refuse to acknowledge that they too could create such a net.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DeSantis, like so many elected officials who strip 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/30/nyregion/coronavirus-hospitals-medicaid-budget.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;state healthcare funding&lt;/a&gt; or 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.texastribune.org/2020/04/21/texas-dan-patrick-economy-coronavirus/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tell the elderly it&amp;rsquo;s their patriotic duty to sacrifice themselves for the economy&lt;/a&gt;, knows that it&amp;rsquo;s smart politics to collapse the range of choices presented to the public to &amp;ldquo;definitely lose your job&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;possibly get COVID-19&amp;rdquo;. Republicans recognize that the vulnerable who are hurt by their policies (or lack thereof) were likely not going to vote for them anyway and it&amp;rsquo;s safe for Democrats to hew to a similar line because as long as there are sociopaths like 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2020/03/24/covid-19-texas-official-suggests-elderly-willing-die-economy/2905990001/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dan Patrick&lt;/a&gt; on the right, even Cuomo-style Democrats will always be the obvious lesser-of-two-evils choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, Desantis took the all too common responsibility-disappearing act to a new level—not only refusing to keep people safe but placing the blame for the consequences of his inaction on those most hurt by it, blaming 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tampabay.com/news/health/2020/06/19/ron-desantis-blames-florida-farmworkers-for-covid-aid-groups-say-testing-help-came-late/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;overwhelmingly Hispanic farmworkers&amp;rdquo; for the rise in cases&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fdacs.gov/News-Events/Press-Releases/2020-Press-Releases/Statement-by-Commissioner-Nikki-Fried-on-Record-High-COVID-19-Cases&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nevermind that the Governor&amp;rsquo;s statement is factually incorrect&lt;/a&gt; in the mind palaces of many of our leaders, a callous reopening is the only rational choice path forward. Because reopening is inevitable—the only alternative to economic ruin—business owners and consumers can&amp;rsquo;t be blamed for a spike in deaths and cases, after all, they have no moral agency; they are just along for the ride. Not content to cushion the economy&amp;rsquo;s crash with the bodies of workers, those in power now vilify the workers for the crash in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The American state is as vast as the expectations for what it can offer its people in times of crisis are minuscule. Far from offering carrots to incentivize Floridians to stay home and stay safe, DeSantis is reluctant to even brandish a stick at business owners, saying that enforcement of disease-prevention regulations would be 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.miamiherald.com/news/coronavirus/article243685702.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;problematic for a whole host of reasons&amp;hellip; I think we&amp;rsquo;ve just got to trust people, give them opportunity to do good things, make good decisions. I think that works better&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Meanwhile, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.doctorswithoutborders.org/what-we-do/news-stories/news/florida-msf-and-local-health-partners-bring-covid-19-testing-and&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Medecins Sans Frontieres has opened a mission in Florida&lt;/a&gt;, providing care and testing to those feeding Florida while the governor sneers at them and dogwhistles to his supporters.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ANES Headaches and Headscratchers</title>
      <link>/post/anes-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/anes-problems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.electionstudies.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;American National Election Study&lt;/a&gt; (ANES) is one of the longest running survey datasets, stretching back to 1948—offering public opinion researchers excellent continuity over a broad base of questions. ANES data is hosted either as individual survey years, or in the &amp;ldquo;cumulative data file&amp;rdquo; (CDF), which coalesces each biennial (or quadrennial) iteration of the survey into a single dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ANES-CDF certainly hews closer to the ideal of 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://vita.had.co.nz/papers/tidy-data.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;tidy data&lt;/a&gt; than some canned datasets but is not without its share of eccentricities. I&amp;rsquo;m cataloging some of the (occasionally baffling) coding choices made by the ANES here, in the hopes that it might save some other public opinion researcher&amp;mdash;especialy a hapless grad student&amp;mdash;a few &lt;del&gt;minutes&lt;/del&gt; hours of headache down the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-cdf-does-not-include-every-question-from-the-individual-surveys&#34;&gt;The CDF does not include &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; question from the individual surveys.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not so much a mistake on the part of the ANES, but isn&amp;rsquo;t immediately apparent. The cumulative data file does not contain an exhaustive collection of all of the questions asked by the ANES each year. I&amp;rsquo;m currently working on a project involving within-party divisions, and wanted information about primary vote-choice. Thinking I was clever, I opened the cdf 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://electionstudies.org/anes_timeseries_cdf_codebook_var/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;codebook&lt;/a&gt; and tried (to no avail) to find a question asking for whom respondents voted for in presidential primaries. Broken, defeated, and wondering why the ANES wouldn&amp;rsquo;t ask such an obvious question; I wearily turned to Google where I stumbled across the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://electionstudies.org/resources/anes-continuity-guide/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ANES Continuity Guide&lt;/a&gt;. Using the surprisingly well designed tool, I discovered that the question I was hoping to find &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; asked by the ANES occasionally, but for what I&amp;rsquo;m sure is a &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; good reason is excluded from the CDF (please version control the CDF).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the variable you want to pull isn&amp;rsquo;t in the CDF, still take the time to look through the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://electionstudies.org/resources/anes-continuity-guide/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;continuity guide&lt;/a&gt;. The ANES may have what you&amp;rsquo;re looking for if you&amp;rsquo;re willing to stitch together a few different files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-codebookhttpselectionstudiesorganes_timeseries_cdf_codebook_var-seems-to-be-wrong-about-na-values&#34;&gt;The 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://electionstudies.org/anes_timeseries_cdf_codebook_var/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;codebook&lt;/a&gt; seems to be wrong about &lt;code&gt;NA&lt;/code&gt; values.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/7-point-codebook.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;anes codebook screenshot&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the ANES-CDF 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://electionstudies.org/anes_timeseries_cdf_codebook_var/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;codebook&lt;/a&gt;, NA values are given a numeric code. For example, the codebook tells us that the 7-point party ID variable is coded such that &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; indicates &lt;code&gt;NA&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;INAP&lt;/code&gt; indicates that the question was not asked. Similarly, the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://electionstudies.org/anes_timeseries_cdf_codebook_var/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;codebook&lt;/a&gt; says that feeling thermometers are coded such that &lt;code&gt;98&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;99&lt;/code&gt; indicate &lt;code&gt;Don&#39;t Know&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;NA&lt;/code&gt; respectively, while &lt;code&gt;-8&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;-9&lt;/code&gt; represent &lt;code&gt;Don&#39;t Know&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;NA&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;code&gt;VCF9255&lt;/code&gt; (satisfaction with democracy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s not rely on the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://electionstudies.org/anes_timeseries_cdf_codebook_var/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;codebook&lt;/a&gt;. Using &lt;code&gt;Rcode&lt;/code&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ll pull a few variables to check how they&amp;rsquo;re coded:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;# pulling anes-cdf from a GitHub repository
cdf &amp;lt;- rio::import(&amp;quot;https://github.com/RobLytle/intra-party-affect/raw/master/data/raw/cdf-raw-trim.rds&amp;quot;)%&amp;gt;%
  select(VCF0004, #year
         VCF0218, #Democrat FT
         VCF0224, #Republican FT
         VCF0301, #Party ID
         VCF9255,  #Satisfied/not with Democracy
          #education 7cat
         )%&amp;gt;%
  rename(year = VCF0004, #renaming variables
         ft_dem = VCF0218,
         ft_rep = VCF0224,
         pid_7 = VCF0301,
         democ_satis = VCF9255,
         )%&amp;gt;%
  filter(year &amp;gt;= 2004)%&amp;gt;% # democ_satis isn&#39;t asked until 2004, so I&#39;m trimming the data for ease of illustration
  glimpse()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Rows: 13,718
## Columns: 5
## $ year        &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; 2004, 2004, 2004, 2004, 2004, 2004, 2004, 2004, 2004, 2...
## $ ft_dem      &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; NA, 85, 15, 50, 30, 30, 30, 70, 50, 15, 85, 60, 70, 40,...
## $ ft_rep      &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; NA, 40, 85, 97, 85, 30, 60, 50, 30, 97, 60, 60, 50, 60,...
## $ pid_7       &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; 4, 3, 7, 4, 7, 4, 7, 2, 3, 7, 3, 3, 3, 6, 3, 3, 3, 6, 4...
## $ democ_satis &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; 2, 1, 2, NA, 1, 3, 1, 1, NA, 1, 2, 2, 3, 2, 2, 3, NA, 1...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://tibble.tidyverse.org/reference/glimpse.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;tidyverse::glimpse()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;ing the data, we can tell that there are, in fact, &lt;code&gt;NA&lt;/code&gt; values, contrary to what the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://electionstudies.org/anes_timeseries_cdf_codebook_var/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;codebook&lt;/a&gt; says, but let&amp;rsquo;s be certain. I&amp;rsquo;ll throw together a quick visualization of the frequency of each variable&amp;rsquo;s values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;# Making quick ggplots of frequencies
democ &amp;lt;- ggplot(cdf, aes(x = democ_satis)) +
  geom_bar(aes(y = stat(count))) 

pid &amp;lt;- ggplot(cdf, aes(x = pid_7)) +
  geom_bar(aes(y = stat(count)))+
  scale_x_continuous(breaks = seq(1, 7, by = 1))+
  labs(y = &amp;quot; &amp;quot;)

ft &amp;lt;- cdf%&amp;gt;%
  pivot_longer(ft_dem:ft_rep, names_to = &amp;quot;name&amp;quot;, values_to = &amp;quot;ft&amp;quot;)%&amp;gt;% #combining D and R fts into one column
  filter(ft &amp;gt;= 90)%&amp;gt;%  # just filtering high FTs to make visualization easier
ggplot(aes(x = ft)) +
  geom_bar(aes(y = stat(count))) +
  scale_x_continuous(breaks = seq(90, 100, by = 1)) +
  labs(y = &amp;quot; &amp;quot;)

#putting each visualization into a single object
gridExtra::grid.arrange(democ,
             pid,
             ft,
          ncol = 3)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../post/2020-06-18-an-incomplete-record-of-anes-goof-em-ups.en_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure enough, none of the values &lt;code&gt;DK&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;NA&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;RF&lt;/code&gt; values denoted in the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://electionstudies.org/anes_timeseries_cdf_codebook_var/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;codebook&lt;/a&gt; actually appear in the CDF. It seems as though they were switched to &lt;code&gt;NA&lt;/code&gt; when the dataset was prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-responses-are-truncated&#34;&gt;Some responses are truncated.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feeling thermometer questions ask respondents to rate their warmth towards a group (like &amp;ldquo;Democrats&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Catholics&amp;rdquo;) on a scale from 0–100. As seen above though, the ANES feeling thermometer variables max out at 97. 98 and 99 are (supposedly) reserved for &lt;code&gt;NA&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;Don&#39;t Know&lt;/code&gt;—though that convention is not currently in use. Likely this was done to save space and avoid 3-digit numbers. Size may have been a valid concern in a time before several-terabyte harddrives were commonplace, but serves no purpose now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the researcher&amp;rsquo;s perspective, this truncation is troublesome, but not disastrous. Net group affect—a common measure of polarization (e.g., 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/poq/article-abstract/76/3/405/1894274&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Iyengar, Sood, and Lelkes 2012&lt;/a&gt;)—is measured as &lt;code&gt;\(FT_{in} - FT_{out}\)&lt;/code&gt;. Since the ANES coding scheme essentially subtracts &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt; from a sizeable chunk of respondents&amp;rsquo; in-party scores (notice how many &lt;code&gt;97&lt;/code&gt;s there are relative to other high-end responses) studies that use net group affect or something similar are likely to underestimate the degree of polarization—albeit by a small degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aren&amp;rsquo;t the only instances of truncation or a misleading 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://electionstudies.org/anes_timeseries_cdf_codebook_var/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;codebook&lt;/a&gt; entry, 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://gojiberries.io/2010/12/29/coding-issues-in-the-anes-cumulative-file/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is an example of a variable in which the variable&amp;rsquo;s levels varied year to year—not noted in its 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://electionstudies.org/anes_timeseries_cdf_codebook_var/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;codebook&lt;/a&gt; entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;takeaways&#34;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson here is to always validate for yourself what is claimed by a dataset&amp;rsquo;s documentation. These problems usually are not deadly, just easily missed. Implementing some kind of version control on the CDF would presumably make it easier to improve the dataset and fix these headaches without breaking existing scripts/analyses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
