<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>politics | Rob Lytle</title>
    <link>/category/politics/</link>
      <atom:link href="/category/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>politics</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0ee476e0f8e52f1f1634ede288429d6f_11738_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>politics</title>
      <link>/category/politics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ron Desantis and the Banality of Evil</title>
      <link>/post/banality-of-desantis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/banality-of-desantis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a painfully predictable turn of events, Covid-19 cases have begun to skyrocket in Florida, a few short weeks after state and local government began the process of (prematurely) rolling back public health safeguards. This week, Governor Ron DeSantis performed an impressive rhetorical trick, abdicating not just his own responsibility for the death and illness—but that of all the wealthy consumers and business owners agitating for a return to normalcy at the expense of workers&amp;rsquo; lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desantis says 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/jun/20/florida-covid19-surge-reopening-governor-desantis-coronavirus&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re not shutting down. We&amp;rsquo;re going to go forward. We&amp;rsquo;re not rolling back. You have to have society function&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and that 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.miamiherald.com/news/coronavirus/article243685702.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The disease burden is not as significant as it was in March and April,&amp;rdquo; it&amp;rsquo;s “Very important to point out. We’re in a much better position than we were in March or April.”&lt;/a&gt;. According to DeSantis, to &amp;ldquo;shut down&amp;rdquo; (institute necessary and reasonable public health protections) the state now would do more harm to the people of Florida than the Coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, I take DeSantis at his word. I think he is entirely correct that &lt;em&gt;under his administration&lt;/em&gt; reinstating necessary physical distance and stat-at-home orders would be terrible for the median Floridian; but this is entirely by design. In the abscence of a robust state or federal response a second round of closings would be financially ruinous for hundreds of thousands if not millions of Floridians—but this is a false dichotomy. DeSantis would have you believe that the paths forward are predetermined: either we can plunge the state and country into depression, or we can grease the gears of the economy with the infected sputum of the poorest and most vulnerable members of our society. DeSantis, like so many leaders, is loathe to use the power of the state to protect its people and too craven to tell them as much. While countries like 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.canada.ca/en/revenue-agency/campaigns/covid-19-update/covid-19-benefits-credits-support-payments.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Canada &lt;/a&gt; deploy their modest social safety nets to ameliorate the economic costs of prudent health policy, executives and legislators in the U.S. refuse to acknowledge that they too could create such a net.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DeSantis—not unlike Cuomo, Newsom, and Abbott— knows that it&amp;rsquo;s smart politics to collapse the range of choices presented to the public to &amp;ldquo;definitely lose your job&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;possibly get covid&amp;rdquo;. Republicans recognize that the vulnerable who are hurt by their policies (or lack thereof) were likely not going to vote for them anyway and it&amp;rsquo;s safe for Democrats to hew to a similar line because, after all, what are the poor to do—vote for a Republican? Fat chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DeSantis this week took the all too common rhetorical disappearing act to a new level, not only refusing to keep people safe, but placing the blame for the consequences of his inaction on those most hurt by it, blaming 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tampabay.com/news/health/2020/06/19/ron-desantis-blames-florida-farmworkers-for-covid-aid-groups-say-testing-help-came-late/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;overwhelmingly hispanic farm workers for the rise in cases&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Not the companies forcing them to work, not his own administration for failing to provide a realistic alternative to putting themselves in danger while DeSantis and his donors pine away for a freshly greased economic machine.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
